Guide to the Basil Lee Whitener Papers, 1889-1968
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Personal Series, 1889-1968and undated,primarily 1957-1968
  - Subject Files
    - Whitener, John Morgan, 1960-1966 (Box 300, Folder 6-8)
      Morgan Whitener is the oldest son of the Congressman. These papers relate to such matters as Morgan's attendance at Virginia Episcopal School in Lynchburg and Duke University, and an automobile accident of the son in August, 1964, in Colorado.
  - General Files
    - Biographical and Genealogical Information,1937, 1956-1965and undated (Box 301, Folder 1)
    - Financial Papers, 1958-1968
      These papers primarily concern Whitener's personal and family finances.
      - Bank Statements, 1965-1967
        All of the bank statements that came with this collection were retained as a sample of Whitener's activities and expenditures.
        - 1. Citizens National Bank, Gastonia, N.C. In1967,there is a brief bank statement for Basil Whitener for Congress. (Box 301, Folder 2-4)
        - 2. House of Representatives, U.S. Office of the Sergeant at Arms, Washington, D. C.
          - Papers,1965 (Box 301, Folder 5-6)
          - Papers, 1966-1967 (Box 302, Folder 1-4)
      - Checkbook Stubs, 1963-1967
        These are unidentified as to bank, but are probably for Whitener's personal account at Citizens National Bank in Gastonia.
        - 1. Nos. 1-301, 1963, Dec. 20-1964, Sept. 22 (Box 303, Folder 1)
        - 2. Nos. 302-596, 1964, Oct. 13-1965, Aug.5 (Box 303, Folder 2)
        - 3. Nos. 597-885, 1965, June 29-1966, Mar. 17 (Box 303, Folder 3)
        - 4. Nos. 886-1185, 1966, Mar. 22-Oct. 5 (Box 303, Folder 4)
        - 5. Nos. 1186-1482, 1966, Oct. 6-1967, Aug.7 (Box 303, Folder 5)
      - Income Tax, 1956-1968and undated
        Included are copies of Whitener's tax returns and other supporting documents relating to such matters as airline travel. The majority of the items are from 1963 to 1967.
        - Papers, 1956-1963 (Box 303, Folder 6)
        - Papers, 1964-1968and undated (Box 304, Folder 1-5)
      - Telephone Expenses, 1967-1968 (Box 304, Folder 6)
        These are vouchers of the House of Representatives for reimbursement for official telephone service outside the District of Columbia..., and are for Whitener's district office in Gastonia.
    - Miscellany, 1954-1968and undated (Box 304, Folder 7)
    - Clippings, 1953-1968Oversize items have been placed in the Picture Cabinet. (Box 305, Folder 1-4)
    - Printed Material, 1956-1968and undated
      Many Christmas cards and other types of cards were pulled and added to the Card Collection in this department.
      - Papers, 1956-1962 (Box 305, Folder 5-6)
      - Papers, 1963-1968and undated (Box 306, Folder 1-2)
    - Pictures, 1960-1967Entries were made for the Picture File for many of these photographs.
      - Pictures: Prominent Persons (Box 306, Folder 3)
      - Pictures: Vietnam Trips, 1966-1967 (Box 306, Folder 4)
      - Pictures: Whitener (Box 306, Folder 5)
      - Pictures: Whitener with various groups (Box 306, Folder 6-7)
    - Oversize Folders: (Box 307)
      - Clippings (Box 307)
      - Moore, Dan Killian (Box 307)